[SPEAKER_00]: Well, let's start with this one question.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's quite common.
[SPEAKER_00]: How to make sati continuous?
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, how to be mindful of the right thing continuously.
[SPEAKER_00]: You were speaking of it yesterday.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, simple answer is by understanding what sati is.
[SPEAKER_01]: By abandoning the notion that sati pertains to that momentary-momentary, moment-to-moment awareness or something like that, that's simply a contradiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't... it can't exist like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what I'm interested in is the sati which is in regard to freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: The relevant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not sati to make my life better.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: To make me more productive, or smarter, more intelligent, more focused.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, not even... not necessarily just that, but even like... even people who are into meditation techniques and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: The idea of sati is that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Observing from moment to a moment to a moment to a moment, and then you have the uninterrupted mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: But mindfulness is not structured moment to moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's structured in a... in a... in a different... differently... different hierarchy of more general things, more general intentions, more general...
[SPEAKER_01]: States of mind, basically, whereby if you get established upon them, then the particular things, no matter how fast, how fleeting they're occurring, your mindfulness is not affected by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if your mindfulness is established upon particular, fleeting things, then your mindfulness will be flying away with them as they cease.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the relevant manner, basically, yeah,
[SPEAKER_01]: Establishing your mind at a more general phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, and it can be various things in terms of establishing mindfulness upon them, so you don't have to... it's not like fixed, you must establish upon this.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can use your body, you can use your feelings, you can use your thoughts, you can use the motivations behind your actions, you can do all those things to establish your mind in regard to things you're doing on a particular level, and that's already mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in terms of, like, if you wanted the most direct answer how to be mindful that's relevant to the suffering and freedom from it, well, you have to be mindful of your feelings or of the present feeling, whichever that is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even with the feelings, you can see even they have this kind of hierarchy of more general and more ambiguous and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, because even the most kind of vague
[SPEAKER_01]: The five-elven mood is basically... you can regard it almost as a feeling, because it has a certain feel to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you might not be able to define what you perceive in terms of that mood as a phenomenon, but you can certainly say, yeah, it feels a bit... it's a bit heavy.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, okay, you're perceiving heaviness, but all of those things you perceive, how they feel?
[SPEAKER_01]: Eh... it's a bit unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a bad mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, you can have the most obvious, oh, this is a very pleasurable feeling, that's coming as a result of me having disagree... having agreeable perceptions, such as, eh... nice taste, beautiful sights, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you... if you're obviously... if you're only concerned with those things, then the... when those things change, when those things move too quickly, your mindfulness will not remain established, because it was... it was established upon them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But say you establish your mindfulness upon the general mood behind these particular things that are arising and sort of interacting with you.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you establish your mind upon those more general sense of, you know, yeah, my mind feels light and expanded, which is agreeable, which is pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you can then establish your mind upon that level of feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather than the feeling on that level.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, when you do have disagreeable perceptions, they will not induce painful feelings, because your mind is established on the higher feelings being higher than those.
[SPEAKER_01]: And those are like in the suttas, similar.
[SPEAKER_01]: Establish your mind upon the perception of forest, so then, disagreeable perception of the village, when you have to be in the village, will not bother you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's for that very reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, to establish your mind on a higher feeling... A more general feeling, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're saying, if I have an unpleasant feeling, to go to a higher feeling... You could, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If a particular, well, no, if a particular disagreeable feeling bothers you, yeah, you go on a higher feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you know, the ultimate higher feeling is accepting that you will die.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not being afraid of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you realize, okay, so whatever has arisen, whatever arises, it will have to cease, because it's not gonna stay and beset me forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just impossible, inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, you don't even have to think that anymore, when you've thought it sufficient number of times, because then you just know that whatever has arisen, has to cease, for the very reason that it has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing else, nothing other.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the whole idea of the... and that's why people fear pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why everybody fears pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, when it arises, there is implicit assumption that's eternal.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's going to last forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just have that kind of inside... contains that inside fear, that this pain, that I know... that I don't know how to escape from,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's going to sort of affect me forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Although your reason can tell you, no, nothing lasts forever and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: On that emotional level, you're locked.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're locked in the assumption forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the same for pleasure, which is why, for a mind which is not developed, yeah, pleasure is overly intoxicating.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like to the point of oblivion and genuinely developing views that, yeah, you will endure and last forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you start undermining that assumption, then, when the pain arises, you won't feel it, because you know that it's inconceivable for anything to last forever in that sense, in that emotional oppression sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in the same sense, your thirst for essential pleasures or pleasures that you can gain in regard to the world and so on, well, they will also fade gradually, because you realize, oh, that's not lasting forever, so why do I even bother?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why do I even expose myself?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just such a triumphal sort of satisfaction in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the mindfulness, establishing of mindfulness, is basically establishing your mind on a more general level in regard to your present experience here as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if it's not, in regard to the present experience, then it just becomes an an abstraction, whatever you're thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just becomes divorced from what you're actually doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you establish it presently, and you're aware of its presence, so to speak, then then it becomes very real, and obviously very functional establishment, whereby anything lower than that establishment, anything less general,
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything more particular will not... cannot... probably cannot affect you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha said you would be... you should be taking this as far as necessary, in order to develop final freedom.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, in the... in this... in the... in that sutra I mentioned, upon the perceptions of the forest, you bend the perceptions of the village,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, he recognizes, okay, so now, when I go into the village, I'm not affected by any perceptions that I see there, agreeable or disagreeable, because my mind is properly, fully established upon the perceptions of the life experience as a whole in the forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, he also recognizes, disturbances can still come on account of these perceptions in the forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: If something happens in that forest, I could lose my mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, he takes it step further, then he establishes his mind upon the perceptions of Earth.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, whether he's in the forest, or even more lower in the village, or even lower than that, in a layman's house, crowded house, then he won't be affected, because his mind is fully set, fully established upon the perception of Earth.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, wherever he is on this Earth, he'll be mindful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Presently.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, theoretically, he could lose that mindfulness of being established upon the perception of Earth if he was to leave the Earth, to fly into space or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if somebody is able to establish their mind to such a level of perception of Earth, then they could easily establish it upon the perception of space, upon the perception of those general phenomena that pertain to the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he would be fine even in space, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how do you make that perception of Earth to not be abstract?
[SPEAKER_01]: You make it by discerning it in your present experience, right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But also, in order to discern it, you need to know what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or at least, you need to have some clue.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it's important to basically learn and inform yourself from the suttas and then ponder and then discern it as a phenomenal present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not discerning in theory only, because that's not a discernment.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's an abstraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is the present thinking, and there is the abstract thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: And usually, people can't distinguish the two, and then, they kind of disregard thinking altogether.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's just a very bad idea.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you think about solidity... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's an image, that kind of image of solidity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Surrounding... A concept of... Concept of solidity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Uh, but when with feelings, that's kind of... No, because feelings don't appear as as as concepts, because there will be a perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're being felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to use the faculty of feeling to feel, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, uh, I think, again, what was it?
[SPEAKER_01]: My teaching is for the one who feels.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, his teaching is for the one who knows how to feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just sort of being liable to feeling, it's not enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everybody is that.
[SPEAKER_01]: They actually have to know, to discern, how to feel, and then you will know the feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because most people think they perceive it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Most people think, when they feel, they're actually perceiving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when you say feeling, pleasant feeling... Yeah, you're already... See, that's what you're perceiving.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a concept of pleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some sort of whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I can designate a pleasant feeling, but that designation is on the level of perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: Perception of sound, perception of utterance, perception of... even a perception of a mental image of either words, pleasant feeling written, or some pleasant experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, all those perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: And
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't not have the perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, you can't not have feelings, because they are inseparable, perception and feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what you can know is how to feel in regard to that which you perceive, and not think that that which you perceive is the same thing that you're feeling, because then there will be a perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, simultaneously, while you're perceiving, you're always simultaneously that feeling on a level of feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: And those two levels cannot mix.
[SPEAKER_01]: They cannot come together.
[SPEAKER_01]: They cannot communicate.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're actually, like, blind to each other.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your feelings don't know about your perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, your perceptions know about your feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's your assumption that it's the same, that it's different, that it's both same and different.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's neither the same nor different in regard to perception and feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: You mix it all up, and then you assume, and then what you perceive is what you feel, what you feel is what you perceive.
[SPEAKER_01]: But feeling feels, perception perceives, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And whether that thing is same, or different, or neither, or both, that doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: But one is more general than the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: What?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, if you would say one is more general than the other, then they would be comparable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And being comparable is only the form of relationship.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I said, they completely are unaware of each other.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because
[SPEAKER_01]: Feeling is completely unaware of perception, and perception is completely unaware of feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can, you can, you can free both of them from assumptions and from the sense of self and everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if they were a relationship, then they would be the agent in control of them, in regard to them, external to them, internal to them, whichever way.
[SPEAKER_00]: What about this, like, joy?
[SPEAKER_00]: Joy, in one case from meditation,
[SPEAKER_00]: Pity.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, remember we spoke about to will that, to get that going.
[SPEAKER_00]: And one can do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: One can generate pity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, pity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pali pity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Joy.
[SPEAKER_00]: One can generate joy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: As an act of will.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, if you, your mind is
[SPEAKER_00]: Very depressed or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Scattered.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unrestrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have that much practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you could, at some stage, do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that feels good.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that way, it seems like I'm in control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Good feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'd be in... Well, you think you would be in control if you then appropriate that good feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: That good feeling is just the result of a certain way of attending and intending.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's... that's absolutely fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you shouldn't fear that pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: When the Buddha said pleasure in regard to jhānas and so on, he realized, oh, hold on, I don't actually have to... because initially, he was disregarding all of the pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any pleasant feeling was bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, when he started developing jhānas, he realized, no, actually, these feelings are not underlined by any of those unwholesome things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is no reason to fear this.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the contrary, I should cultivate this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, it was declared as the ultimate way of basically getting the right view, developing jhānas, and then you'll be a fully developed arahant in both ways, as they say, through full understanding and through full development in regard to your body and meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yeah, it's that good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, it can be that good.
[SPEAKER_01]: whereby you can intentionally, with the right view, not without the right view, but with the right view, intentionally cultivate joy, or rapture, or whatever, and it won't be unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you would know it, if it's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're just, it's just an intent, you're just intending it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just the result of the intention that's occurring, not yours to begin
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't pertain to the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's not unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: However, obviously, you can appropriate that joy, which is why Kutujana can develop jhānas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, he'll abandon lots of sensual cravings as a result of it, because this is much more sublime, much more refined.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yes, you could.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like,
[SPEAKER_01]: You would be... you wouldn't be doing it rightly if you then start appropriating that joy and feeling you are in control of that joy, this joy's mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But with the right view, that wouldn't happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you would just have the proper practice of developing joy and the right view that sort of sees through any occurrence of lust, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it wouldn't be before long that the mind would be completely free from all the hindrances with that development.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there wouldn't be any agitation, there wouldn't be any anxiety, even hardships would feel relatively easy, because the mind gets elevated.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're saying the hindrances won't come up again?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I say you become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: With the right view and the jhānas, you'll become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I don't want to say feeling is always in the background, but... Yeah, I see what you mean, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't want to... You can, you can, you can, well...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think, initially, you probably have to, because that's, that's where you're going to find it, because, uh, the mind is, uh...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not... Too used to, too much established upon perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, obviously, mind needs to learn how to feel, how to discern feeling among the, you know, things that it perceives.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, in that sense, it's in the background.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't find it where you perceive it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll find it simultaneously in regards to that which you perceive.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, you have to refrain from attending to the feeling as if it's a perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to refrain from attending to the feeling as if you will see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not actually behind because...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's right there all the time in regard to whatever you perceive it to.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, obviously, it has its own
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, each domain has its own laws, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not as diverse as perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't move as quickly as perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, obviously, it's much more subtle than perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: Beyond perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's beyond in terms of it has nothing to do with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're not to the same place, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I mean, place is already applicable only to perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: It comes as a result of perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: Space and place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feeling is in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's just like two dimensions, but you're just used to one.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the other one is constantly in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see, with feeling, it sounds like it will be unconditioned.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it will be, when you completely let go of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the teaching is for the one who feels, and that's why he teaches only suffering and freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the whole dhamma in there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, nibbāna is pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, no feeling can touch you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, you don't feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't feel anything, and that's the extreme, like, peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: The arahant will always see the distinction.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, he won't see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He'll feel it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, he feels it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He'll feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: He'll feel, then feeling, and he'll see it from the point of view of perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, he won't try to see his feeling, nor will he try to feel his perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: He'll feel, he'll perceive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, feeling will feel, perception will perceive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Intentions will intend.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you can attend to a feeling, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, but see, in order to attend to a feeling, you have to, well, you have to use the proper attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you don't know how to attend to the feeling, well, you attend by the means that you're used to, and those are the means of perception, which means you won't be attending to the feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll still feel it, because feeling is an aggregate.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't not feel it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just you won't be able to discern what feeling is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't be able to know the feeling until you learn how to feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, feeling in itself is not enough for you to learn how to feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feeling just affects you, just hits you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Good and bad are neutral.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by learning how to feel, then, you can eventually transcend it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole domain of feeling and all other domains, obviously.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how to pay attention?
[SPEAKER_01]: By learning how to feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: By recognizing that at any given time of your experience as a whole, the feeling is present there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if I ask you now how you... And that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can discern how to feel because there is
[SPEAKER_01]: An implicit knowledge of the feeling, or a degree of recognition.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe it's not to the level of knowledge, but certainly...
[SPEAKER_00]: If you ask me, how do I feel?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, if I ask you, how do you feel now?
[SPEAKER_01]: You would be able to answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you say, well, I don't quite know.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means, okay, so you feel neither like this, nor like that, which means you feel kind of neutral, veering towards unpleasant, because you don't really know it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, bored or whatever, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, I've already answered.
[SPEAKER_00]: I've given some sort of... these words to describe that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that doesn't still necessarily mean that you have confused the two.
[SPEAKER_01]: That you've started... Or rather, you can describe the feeling in terms of designation, in terms of perception, but you won't assume that that perception stands for that which you feel at the time when you're describing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you can be mindful of the feeling
[SPEAKER_01]: Or feelings, as they arise respectively, at any time, at any place, in any situation, because they're not directly linked to the actual, like, particular sort of perceptions, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, they arise as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: Perception, feeling, and intention arise together, cease together.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when there is a disagreeable perception, or whatever, that has arisen,
[SPEAKER_01]: For an untrained mind, there is most likely going to be unpleasant feeling as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that doesn't necessarily have to be the case.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because it doesn't have to be the case, freedom from disagreeable perceptions in terms of suffering is possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if perception perceives and feeling feels, it has nothing to do with you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a feeling from disagreeable perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Disagreeable perceptions for Putujan means suffering, means feeling pain, feeling unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that mix, or rather that mixing up, that wrong assumption in regard to perception and feeling, feeling, perception, the whole thing, it's so hardened that now it's a solid thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for him, disagreeable means pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Disagreeable perceptions, discomfort, any of that kind, means emotional pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he needs to kind of unravel the whole thing, the whole assumption, and then
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you can perceive, or rather, if your experience can let the perceptions perceive and feelings feel, you become redundant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: My sense of self becomes redundant and disappears.
[SPEAKER_01]: Temporarily, based on the intention of that establishment, upon that establishment, but with the right view, that's all it takes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, the view of the self will disappear, the views of the conceit will disappear, and so on, and then, yeah, you will be not around.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because perception perceives, feeling feels.
[SPEAKER_01]: Intention intends.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this sense itself now, that lingers in regard and kind of hovers over these things, you realize, well, that's just another perception, isn't it, that perceives this feeling in regard to it, that feels an intention in regard to it, that intends.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, the subtler sense of I am in regard to that, oh, well, the fact that I was just able to designate it means that's another perception that perceives, that has a feeling in regard to it, that feels an intention, that intends.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can push this infinitely until you get tired and you realize, oh, this whole idea, this whole notion, this whole concept of I am lingering, is just a more subtle perception in regard to the arisen perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a more subtle feeling in regard to the arisen feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a more subtle intention in regard to the arisen intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, all you're going to have is feeling, perception, intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you kind of drill that long enough, any notion of me and I am,
[SPEAKER_01]: It just fades, evaporates, like heating a pan that had water in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, if there's a lot of water, you might have to heat it longer, but eventually everything will evaporate and then you can stop heating it.
[SPEAKER_01]: By knowing what jhāna is?
[SPEAKER_01]: By not mixing your feelings with your perceptions?
[SPEAKER_01]: By learning how to feel?
[SPEAKER_01]: By being mindful of your feelings?
[SPEAKER_01]: All of those things can become a basis for your jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: The one thing of mine that I can see that I did most of my things in my life was because of boredom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Most things I did, yeah, getting involved in certain sensualities, you know, drinking, smoking, the whole business, watching movies, it's boredom.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think most people get, yeah, it's the
[SPEAKER_01]: Boredom and fear of boredom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fear of boredom, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like genuine fear of boredom.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, I'm a bit bored, but you actually, everybody, well, two generals, fear boredom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because when you do get extremely, extremely bored, extremely, extremely bored... Well, then you start losing, losing your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is, obviously, for somebody who is all about their sense of self, it's very frightening.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why boredom freaks people out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can lose your sense of self, not in them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, not lose in terms of... fully extinguish it, as another hand.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, basically, start feeling like you're not letting go of the sense of self, yet it's being taken away.
[SPEAKER_01]: All right, but how is it taken away?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's taken away through boredom, basically, simply because boredom is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, you've been pursuing, everybody's been pursuing pleasures, habitually, and now they became dependent upon the pursuit of pleasures.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, when there are no pleasures, even if there is no particular pain, so it's just boredom, it's just a neutral feeling, but because you're so dependent upon pleasures, that neutral feeling starts to feel very unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And not knowing the escape from unpleasant, you fear it even more.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're affected by it even more.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, the whole thing of boredom just shows you that deep down, inside of your very sense of self, that you hold very dearly, you're not in control even of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that freaks you out.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why in solitary confinement, people often go mad.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when they come out, they're like, oh, he's a different person now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, he would be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, you know,
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be, for somebody with the right view, solitary confinement would probably result in arahantship.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for those without the right view, even coming across nibbāna, it would freak them out, as they did in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they would understand the goal of dhamma when the Buddha... when the Buddha was pointing at this all.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will annihilate us, they will kill us, they will destroy us.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they... their minds, their attention is still very rooted.
[SPEAKER_01]: They have completely gratuitously assumed sense of self, but that is real as such, and that's all they have at the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why, if in that state of mind, they come across anything they will vaguely indicate they're not in control, there will be quite a good cause for anxiety, for a deep anxiety.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, if you stay with that deep anxiety longer, in the case of prolonged boredom, you'll start freaking out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, you start looking for a way out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not everybody will freak out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some people will say,
[SPEAKER_01]: I want to look if there is a... there is a freedom from this, because I'm not in control of my own very self.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when I say I'm not in control, I don't mean, oh, I can do anything, which is something people end up doing after prolonged boredom.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it means, basically, you have no say in the very foundations of your own being that you take to be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, that's a big contradiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's mine, well, you would have a say, but you have no say.
[SPEAKER_01]: So how can it be yours?
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't know anything but to have it as yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now everything is indicating you that it can't be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you have a choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're able to, you can then just turn a blind eye and run even faster from the fact that you have no say in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And always kind of be just a sort of enough, like, you know, basically you're drowning, but you're just enough space to have, like, a breath of air every now and then.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what most people's lives are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Constant pursuit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's not...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, the types of pursuit are optional.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the reasons for the pursuit for people out there are not optional.
[SPEAKER_01]: They all have to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you don't do it, you start sinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: And where do you sink?
[SPEAKER_01]: You sink in the... basically in the environment that shows you that
[SPEAKER_01]: Things are indifferent to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have no say in your own feelings, in your own intentions, in your own perceptions, yet you take them to be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: That feels basically like you're locked in a car, in a vehicle, that it's running down the hill, full speed, and actually the steering wheel is not working, maybe a little bit, but not in a sense that you can stop the car.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, all you can choose is where you're going to crash.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even that, it's not ultimately up to you, because you might crash even before you reach where you want to crash at.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have you have a limited degree of control within the ultimate lack of control.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, right.
[SPEAKER_00]: It sounds like suicide, you know, like the acts of suicide, you can... you don't really... Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's what I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can only kind of aim at the body and then wait for death to come.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's... that's... that's... well, that's... that's basically... and even that, it's not... even that death that comes cannot be yours, any more than any other thing that you could do during your life can be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, one alternative is to keep running away from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The other alternative is to then recognize that this
[SPEAKER_01]: This is not a good deal.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the contradiction that your existence is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I'm here.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: I feel things are mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I'm not saying it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then I better make the effort and abandon that notion of I am and things are mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then I won't be having to live this contradiction, which is actually unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So be at the bottom of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Extreme boredom, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is nothing for you to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing for you to have.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, there never was.
[SPEAKER_00]: There never was, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's what boredom feels like.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Non-activity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Abiding in non-activity.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they see, like, obviously,
[SPEAKER_01]: Boredom, as a designation, it's already... it's already defined by Kutujanans, and it has... it has... it has a very negative connotation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Boredom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, see, it has a negative connotation, but it also implies quite some... quite some self-deception as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm bored.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of... it's kind of all right, but I don't like to be bored.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, actually, boredom is quite serious, because you might kind of try to dismiss it by saying, oh, it's just boredom.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's just bored.
[SPEAKER_01]: Leave him bored a bit longer and then you'll see.
[SPEAKER_01]: He'll start falling apart.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everybody would start falling apart.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, putujana would start falling apart.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But more accurately, it's a neutral feeling that's obviously for putujana.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not known.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's being feared.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's bored.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's anxiety.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's whatever else that comes out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you actually recognize it as such,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, recognizing in regard to, like, lowlier feelings of of sensual pleasure and sensual discomfort and so on, then you you actually know this is peaceful.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is more sublime.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's peace.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's neutral.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's quite pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: In order to find it pleasant, you need to elevate your mind to that level.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to train in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the mind starts down in the gutter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Always
[SPEAKER_01]: Just a different extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you have to work your way up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: When someone is bored, in a negative sense, the mind starts to, you know, freak out, and you start craving, even craving those old senses, or more sensual things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because basically, that offers itself, as you spoke before, the sensual pleasure,
[SPEAKER_01]: Kind of feels like a like a quick fix.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereby, not just that you get the pleasure of the sense that you're engaging in, but you also get the pleasure of just kind of avoiding this boring pain, this heavy anxious threat behind this boredom.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the pleasure makes that disappear, seemingly, and provides you with the pleasure on top of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like a double whammy.
[SPEAKER_00]: That if you don't go into sensual pleasures, you just crave for them.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just double the suffering right there, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you've got enough, you know, you're bored.
[SPEAKER_00]: Initially, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have enough restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you crave...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you suffer on account of boredom, because you're ignorant in regard to it, and then you suffer on account of uncontrollable craving that you are not, kind of, covering up through giving in to that craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have a double, double suffering that's being present.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly how it is, how it has to be in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why vinaya, the sīla, has to come first.
[SPEAKER_01]: The restraint, the precept, has to come first.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a dhamma, but there wouldn't be any dhamma without it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it has to come first, and then you can start building within that.
[SPEAKER_00]: From there, you can see craving equals suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Craving equals suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: You were craving for this body to be absent, to be not present.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are craving for pleasure to be present.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have craving on both levels, you have suffering on both levels.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't suffer, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't suffer because you're not pursuing your desires.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that non-pursuit of desires shows you the craving behind them, which is why you suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it takes time to discern that, because craving, you give in, you go after the desire, and pain disappears.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or so it seems.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the pain disappears because you stop craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you stop craving because you have the assumption that you satisfied your desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that assumption has nothing to do with the actual satisfaction of your senses or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just an assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why, next time, you probably need more of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And more of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And harder scratch.
[SPEAKER_01]: And harder push.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for what?
[SPEAKER_01]: For the same assumption of, OK, now I'm fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Body might feel, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: At ease, temporarily.
[SPEAKER_01]: So craving disappears, and then suffering disappears.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you think suffering disappeared because you satisfied your desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you didn't, because when craving comes back, and it does always comes back, because it's not distinguished, suffering appears.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then again, you don't blame the craving for that suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: You blame, oh, it's a new desire that I need to satisfy.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's actually, if there is a presence of craving, means suffering is present.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot suffer
[SPEAKER_01]: On any other account, except one single account, presence of craving, in regard to the most extreme circumstances, the most extreme discomfort situations, experiences, if there is suffering present, it's not because of them, it's because of the presence of craving in regard to those circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's... that's why the people... restraint for people means pain, and they think
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm hurting now because I'm holding myself back.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm hurting because I'm restrained.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Restraint is not... basically, restraint is a side thing whereby if you engage in restraint, what is revealed is that craving is suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing else.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in order to see that, you have to stop, you have to practice restraint sufficiently
[SPEAKER_01]: For you to know that you should stop blaming for pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stop assuming that that is the reason for your pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the sensuality in itself is inseparable from craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the perceptions of sensuality are inseparable from craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: They imply craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, you perceiving sensual desire means craving is present, means suffering is present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you restraining yourself in regard to the pursuit of the sensual desire, pain arises immediately.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're saying no to yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that pain is not because you said no.
[SPEAKER_01]: That pain is because saying no to yourself revealed the underlying setup of presence of craving is very painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that pain, how can you deal with it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Either by extinguishing craving, which is for most people, well, impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: They simply don't know how
[SPEAKER_01]: You have not been instructed, have not heard a dhamma, you have no concept of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only way... like, it's not really escape, but the only way they could approximate the escape would be giving in.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, again, happens exactly what I said before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, not just that you kind of obscured the pain that has arisen, but now you also got the pleasure of the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you kind of feel, oh, this is good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I avoided the pain and I got pleasure as a result of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's... you can't ask for more.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the problem is, the underlying setup of presence of craving, presence of suffering, not just that it hasn't been affected or resolved, it just has been fortified more.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the more you pursue desires, the more you'll crave, which means the more... the more the craving is present, the more the suffering is present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence the simile of scratching the itch.
[SPEAKER_01]: You get that relief temporarily while you're scratching it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Overall, you're making it much, much worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: Next time, it will scratch harder, and harder, and harder, until eventually, you're just like a mangy doll that's not even aware of it, but it's perpetually, perpetually just scratching and ripping its skin open.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it doesn't even know it anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just doing it as a habit, just to scratch, just...
[SPEAKER_01]: Mind is elsewhere, and you're just ripping it, just scratching it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's, you know, quite, quite, quite only human existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's backboarding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_00]: It feels like you're done.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: When there's no need to resist happening.
[SPEAKER_01]: You feel like, it feels like you're being annihilated.
[SPEAKER_01]: Gradually.
[SPEAKER_00]: That can be quite a pleasant thing, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you start having...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're not holding on to the contradiction of I am, while that I am is being annihilated, that's a discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you avoid, you overcome that discrepancy, well, by basically not holding to I am anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then there won't be any discrepancy splitting, hurting you, annihilating you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's quite pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're here.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's deliberation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, as in a monastic life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let me just get from practice to practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're calling me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Go on, sorry.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, in monastic life, you can't quite... well, I came across the plot anyway... that extreme boredom, and then just constant thoughts of... you're dying, and then ideas of how to survive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Try and, you know, your mind goes back to the past.
[SPEAKER_00]: Try to rekindle yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: What about this?
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, don't lose yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: That desperate... Yeah, there's aspiration.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...to survive for that self.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would revolve around things, around the memories, around the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: They were dear, they were significant to your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if I had to be bored, I'm sure that would come up again, that desperate attempt to survive.
[SPEAKER_00]: But being able to watch, being able to be...
[SPEAKER_01]: Being able to not act out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, to not act out of fear of boredom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not act out of fear, full stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, to allow that boredom and that fear to arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And just sit through it, kind of thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Watch it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If then something happens that had nothing to do with your intention to run away from it, but if something happens...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm just watching a mosquito is trying to enter through the curtain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so...
[SPEAKER_01]: If something happens while you're being bored, but that's not the reason... if that which happens is not the result of you trying to run away, trying to, you know, cover up the boredom,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: What won't be fine is hoping for something to happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: What won't be fine is projecting that which happened, because you must be bored.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that all comes through training and boredom.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll be able to start deciding it through non-distraction,
[SPEAKER_01]: Through restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then it will come.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the more it comes, the more efficient it will become, the more proficient, the more it is, the more it is, better you see it, clearly you see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, oh, look, this is training in peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: Could someone else... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Someone who's not doing anything, just sitting around.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, eh... externally, they might be just sitting around.
[SPEAKER_01]: Internally, they're probably doing a lot of wrong things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: For wrong reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the mind is better off in this direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even when you say people just sit around, they're not doing anything, that tends to them not doing work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they're sitting around means doing things they want to do, which means they're not necessarily bored, just be sitting around.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, nobody likes boredom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, Arjuna likes it, because it's unboredom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sotāpanna appreciates it, because it can make him into an Arjuna.
[SPEAKER_01]: But Puṭṭhārjuna fears it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it can kill him, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, because he doesn't know how to let go of the insense itself, and that creates a rather unbearable discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm holding to this, which now, it's kind of obvious, cannot be mine, yet I cannot not hold on to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it really feels like you're being, kind of, torched from inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, yeah, people lose their minds, often, on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just get depressed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or get really depressed, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Catatonic.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: It always seemed like something was wrong, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: That boredom, something's wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's, again, that's just the view coming from the point of view of sense itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's what it's used to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you start undoing that, all those kind of collateral views will also start fading.